Finding Aid for James G. O'Hara Papers 1958-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Congressional Papers
  - Legislative Files
    - 90th Congress 1967-1968
      - Labor
        - Manpower Development and Training Act, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - National Labor Relations Board (Box 11)
        - Occupational Safety and Health, 3 folders (Box 11)
        - Right-to-Work Legislation (Box 11)
        - Service Contracts Bill (Box 11)
        - Situs Picketing Bill, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Migrant Labor, 4 folders (Box 11)
      - Natural Resources/Pollution
        - General (Box 11)
        - Clinton River (Box 11)
        - Redwoods National Park, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Sleeping Bear Dunes, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Powell, Adam Clayton (Box 12)
      - Prayer in Schools (Box 12)
      - Presidential Debate Bill (Box 12)
      - Reapportionment "Dirksen Amendment" (Box 12)
      - Selective Service, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Social Security, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Supreme Court (Box 12)
      - Transportation
        - General (Box 12)
        - Railroad Strike Bill (Box 12)
      - Urban Riots/Crime Control
        - General, 3 folders (Box 12)
        - Detroit Riot (Box 12)
        - Riot Prevention Bill, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - 91st Congress 1969-1970
      - Anti-Ballistic Missile System (Box 12)
      - Civil Rights
        - General (Box 12)
        - Age Discrimination (Box 12)
        - Equal Employment Opportunity Act Amendments (Box 12)
        - School Desegregation (Box 12)
        - Sex Discrimination at University of Michigan (Box 12)
      - Congressional Reorganization, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Consumer Full Warranty Protection Bill, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Crime
        - General (Box 13)
        - Bethel Church Incident/Judge Crockett (Box 13)
        - Campus Disorder (Box 13)
      - Economic Opportunity Act Amendment-s (Box 13)
      - Education (Box 13)
      - General
        - Aid to Private Schools (Box 13)
        - Busing (Box 13)
        - Elementary and Secondary Education Bill, 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Federal Aid to Education (Box 13)
        - Higher Education Bill (Box 13)
        - Sex Education (Box 13)
      - Eighteen Year Old Vote (Box 13)
      - Electoral College Reform, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Foreign Affairs: Vietnam
        - General, 6 folders (Box 13)
        - General, 2 folders (Box 14)
        - My Lai (Box 14)
        - House Resolution 613 (Box 14)
      - Freedom of the Press (Nixon/Agnew attack on the media) (Box 14)
      - Gun Control (Box 14)
      - HEW Appropriations Bill (Nixon Veto), 4 folders (Box 14)
      - Labor
        - Employment Services Bill (Box 14)
        - Guaranteed Employment Bill (Box 14)
        - Job Corps (Box 14)
        - Manpower Act, 5 folders (Box 14)
        - Mine Safety Bill (Box 14)
        - Occupational Safety Legislation (Box 14)
      - Migrant Labor
        - General (Box 15)
        - Grape Boycott (Box 15)
        - NLRA Coverage (Box 15)
        - Unemployment Compensation (Box 15)
      - Natural Resources/Pollution
        - Air Pollution (Box 15)
        - Auto Emission Control (Box 15)
        - Clinton River
          - Channelization Project, 2 folders (Box 15)
          - Clean-up Project, 2 folders (Box 15)
          - Flood Control, 3 folders (Box 15)
        - Mercury Pollution of St. Clair River (Box 15)
        - National Parks (Box 15)
        - Sea Lamprey Problem (Box 15)
        - Sleeping Bear Dunes, 8 folders (Box 15)
        - Water Pollution (Box 16)
      - Selective Service System (Box 16)
      - Selfridge Air Force Base (Box 16)
      - Tax Reform, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Welfare Reform (Box 16)
    - 92nd Congress 1971-1972
      - Abortion (Box 16)
      - Automobile Insurance (Box 16)
      - Campaign Spending Bill (Box 16)
      - CBS News Contempt Citation (Box 16)
      - Education
        - General (Box 16)
        - Anti-busing Amendment (O'Hara) (Box 16)
        - Busing, 8 folders (Box 16)
        - Comprehensive Child Development Act (Box 17)
        - Desegregation and Busing (Box 17)
        - Education Parks (Box 17)
        - Elementary and Secondary Education Bill (Box 17)
        - Emergency Desegregation Act (Box 17)
        - Federal Aid to Education (Box 17)
        - Fund for the Improvement of Secondary Education (Box 17)
        - Invitations to O'Hara (Box 17)
        - O'Hara's Washington Educators Conference (Box 17)
        - Post-Secondary Education Subcommittee Markup Sessions, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Student Assistance
          - National Direct Student Loans (Box 17)
          - Peace Officers Memorial Scholarship (Box 17)
        - Thank You's to O'Hara (Box 17)
        - Veterans' Cost of Instruction Program (Box 17)
        - Veteran's G.I. Bill Extension (Box 17)
        - Vocational Education (Box 17)
      - Equal Employment Opportunity Enforcement Act (Box 17)
      - Foreign Affairs
        - Lithuania and Ukraine (Box 17)
        - Vietnam
          - General, 5 folders (Box 17)
          - POWs/MIAs, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - United Nations (Box 17)
      - Gun Control "Bayh Bill", 2 folders (Box 18)
      - HEW Appropriation Bill (Box 18)
      - Joint Government Operations Committee (Box 18)
      - Kosciusko National Historic Site (Box 18)
      - Labor
        - General (Box 18)
        - Davis-Bacon Act, 2 folders (Box 18)
        - Fair Labor Standards Act (Box 18)
        - Manpower (Box 18)
        - Minimum Wage (Box 18)
        - Occupational Safety and Health (Box 18)
        - Pension Fund Insurance (Box 18)
        - Public Service Employment (Box 18)
        - Service Contracts Act, 3 folders (Box 18)
        - Sex Discrimination at University of Michigan (Box 18)
        - Situs Picketing (Box 18)
        - Sugarcane Workers (Box 18)
        - Wage and Price Freeze (Box 18)
        - West Coast Dock Strike (Box 18)
      - Migrant Labor
        - General Correspondence (Box 18)
        - Child Labor
          - American Friends Service Committee Report (Box 18)
          - Correspondence (Box 18)
          - Committee Action (Box 18)
          - Proposed Hearings (Box 18)
        - Crew Leader Bill (Box 19)
        - Education (Box 19)
        - Farm Labor Relations Act, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Farm Safety Regulations (Box 19)
        - Food Stamps (Box 19)
        - Grape and Lettuce Boycotts (Box 19)
        - Health Care (Box 19)
        - Housing (Box 19)
        - Illegal Immigrants
          - General (Box 19)
          - Romulo Avaloz Case (Box 19)
        - Manpower Programs (Box 19)
        - OEO Programs (Box 19)
        - O'Hara Press Statements (Box 19)
        - Subcommittee Bills (Box 19)
        - United Farmworkers (Box 19)
        - United Migrants for Opportunity, Inc. (Box 19)
        - Workmen's Compensation (Box 19)
      - National Health Insurance (Box 19)
      - Natural Resources/Pollution
        - General (Box 19)
        - Alaska Native Claims Bill (Box 19)
        - Great Lakes Water Levels, 4 folders (Box 19)
        - National Parks and Recreation Areas (Box 19)
        - Ocean Mammal Protection Bill (Box 19)
        - Sleeping Bear Dunes (Box 19)
        - Wild Horses Bill (Box 19)
      - Office of Economic Opportunity Programs (Box 19)
      - Public Works Acceleration Bill (Box 20)
      - Revenue Sharing Act (Box 20)
      - School Prayer Amendment (Box 20)
      - Social Security Benefit Increase (Box 20)
      - Southeastern Michigan Council of Governments (Box 20)
      - Supersonic Transport (Box 20)
      - Taxes (Box 20)
      - Thank You Letters to O'Hara (Box 20)
      - Veterans' Affairs (Box 20)
      - Welfare Reform-Detroit Hearings, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - 93rd. Congress 1973-1974
      - Abortion, 5 folders (Box 20)
      - Amnesty for Draft Evaders (Box 20)
      - Budget Committee (Box 20)
      - Campaign Finance Reform (Box 20)
      - Capital Punishment (Box 20)
      - Congressional Reform, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Economic Stabilization Act, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Education
        - Amateur Athletics, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - Busing, 5 folders (Box 21)
        - Elementary and Secondary Education Act, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (Box 21)
        - Federal Aid to Education (Box 21)
        - Higher Education
          - General (Box 21)
          - College Tuition
            - Carnegie Commission/CED Reports, 3 folders (Box 21)
            - Low/No Tuition Proposals, 3 folders (Box 21)
            - O'Hara article on Free Tuition (Box 21)
            - O'Hara Two Years Free College Proposal (Box 21)
          - Commendations to O'Hara, 2 folders (Box 21)
          - Eisenhower College (Box 21)
          - Funding Bills, 3 folders (Box 21)
          - Hoover Institute on War, Revolution, and Peace (Box 21)
          - Memoranda to Committee Members (Box 21)
          - Student Assistance
            - General, 4 folders (Box 22)
            - Aid to Law Students (Box 22)
            - Basic Opportunity Grants, 3 folders (Box 22)
            - Guaranteed Student Loan Program, 6 folders (Box 22)
            - Hearings, 4 folders (Box 22)
            - Michigan Colleges (Box 22)
            - National Defense Student Loan Program (Box 22)
            - O'Hara Open Letter on Financial Aid (Box 22)
            - State Commissions (Box 22)
            - Supplementary Educational Opportunity Grants (Box 22)
            - Thank You Letters to O'Hara (Box 22)
            - Work Study Program (Box 22)
          - Subcommittee Minutes (Box 23)
          - Truman Memorial Scholarships (Box 23)
        - Impoundment of Appropriated Funds (Box 23)
        - Invitations to O'Hara (Box 23)
        - Vocational Education (Box 23)
      - Electoral College Reform (Box 23)
      - Foreign Affairs
        - General (Box 23)
        - Aid to Turkey (Box 23)
        - Prisoners of War (Box 23)
        - Vietnam, 3 folders (Box 23)
      - Gun Control, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Hansen Committee on House Organization (Box 23)
      - HEW Appropriations Bill (Box 23)
      - Joint Committee on Congressional Operations (Box 23)
      - Labor
        - Food Stamps for Strikers (Box 23)
        - Manpower Programs (Box 23)
        - Minimum Wage (Box 23)
        - National Employment Priorities Act (Box 23)
        - Occupational Health and Safety (Box 23)
        - Pension Fund Insurance (ERISA), 5 folders (Box 23)
        - Public Service Employment (Box 24)
      - Meat Inspection Standards (Box 24)
      - Migrant Labor (Box 24)
      - National Health Insurance (Box 24)
      - Natural Resources/Pollution
        - General (Box 24)
        - Air and Water Pollution (Box 24)
        - Alaska Pipeline Bill (Box 24)
        - Clinton River (Box 24)
        - Energy Crisis (Box 24)
        - Federal Energy Office (Box 24)
        - Great Lakes Water Levels, 2 folders (Box 24)
        - Isle Royale National Park (Box 24)
        - Land Use Planning Act, 2 folders (Box 24)
        - National Parks and Recreation Areas (Box 24)
        - Sleeping Bear Dunes (Box 24)
        - Strip Mining Bill (Box 24)
      - Nixon Impeachment, 5 folders (Box 25)
      - Nixon Pardon, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Office of Economic Opportunity Phase-out, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Railroads-Abandoned Lines (Box 25)
      - Rockefeller Vice-Presidential Nomination (Box 25)
      - Taxes (Box 25)
      - Youth Summer Sports Programs (Box 25)
    - 94th Congress 1975-1976
      - Abortion (Box 25)
      - Budget Committee, 6 folders (Box 25)
      - Consumer Protection Agency (Box 25)
      - Crime Bill (Box 25)
      - Education
        - General (Box 26)
        - Appropriations Bill (Box 26)
        - Busing, 2 folders (Box 26)
        - Child and Family Services Act, 5 folders (Box 26)
        - Elementary and Secondary Education Act (Box 26)
        - Higher Education
          - General (Box 26)
          - Affirmative Action
            - General, 3 folders (Box 26)
            - Hearings (Box 26)
            - Response to O'Hara Speech (Box 26)
            - Reverse Discrimination (Box 26)
          - Higher Education Act Amendment 1975, 2 folders (Box 26)
          - Higher Education Act Amendments 1976, 2 folders (Box 26)
          - Keppel Task Force (Box 26)
          - O'Hara Press Statements (Box 26)
          - Student Assistance
            - General, 5 folders (Box 27)
            - Accreditation (Box 27)
            - Basic Opportunity Grants, 2 folders (Box 27)
            - Cooperative Education (Box 27)
            - G.I. Bill (Box 27)
            - Guaranteed Student Loan Program, 6 folders (Box 27)
            - Mark-up, 2 folders (Box 27)
            - Migrant Workers (Box 27)
            - Needs Analysis (Box 27)
            - Office of Education Regulations (Box 27)
            - O'Hara Bill, 4 folders (Box 28)
            - O'Hara Half-Cost Proposal (Box 28)
            - State Allocations (Box 28)
            - Trio Programs, 3 folders (Box 28)
            - Work Study, 3 folders (Box 28)
          - Title II (Box 28)
          - Title VI, 2 folders (Box 28)
          - Title IX (Sex Discrimination)
            - General, 5 folders (Box 28)
            - Fraternities and Sororities (Box 28)
            - Hearings (Box 28)
            - O'Hara Bill, 2 folders (Box 29)
            - O'Hara Press Statements (Box 29)
          - Title X (Box 29)
          - Tuition Proposals (Box 29)
        - School Lunch Program, 2 folders (Box 29)
        - Vocational Education (Box 29)
      - Foreign Affairs
        - Foreign Aid (Box 29)
        - Middle East (Box 29)
        - Rhodesian Chrome Import Ban (Box 29)
        - Soviet Bloc (Box 29)
        - Turkish Arms Embargo (Box 29)
        - Vietnam (Box 29)
        - Vietnamese Refugees (Box 29)
      - Great Lakes Conference
        - Appointments to Maritime Commission (Box 29)
        - General Correspondence (Box 29)
        - Lake Water Levels (Box 29)
        - Oil Drilling in Lake Erie (Box 29)
        - Organization and Procedure (Box 29)
        - Reserve Mining Case (Box 29)
        - User Fees (Box 29)
        - Waste Water Discharge (Box 29)
      - Gun Control (Box 29)
      - Hayes, Wayne (Box 29)
      - Labor
        - General (Box 29)
        - Davis-Bacon Act (Box 29)
        - Humphrey-Hawkins Bill (Box 29)
        - Minimum Wage (Box 29)
        - National Labor Relations Board (Box 29)
        - Occupational Safety and Health (Box 29)
        - Pensions (Box 29)
        - Public Service Employment (CETA) (Box 29)
        - Right to Work Laws (Box 29)
        - Situs Picketing Bill, 3 folders (Box 30)
        - Unemployment Compensation (Box 30)
      - Migrant Labor (Box 30)
      - Natural Resources/Pollution
        - General (Box 30)
        - Auto Emission Controls (Box 30)
        - Auto Fuel Efficiency Requirements (Box 30)
        - Clean Air Act-Dingell Amendment (Box 30)
        - Energy, 2 folders (Box 30)
        - Environmental Protection Agency (Box 30)
        - Natural Gas Deregulation (Box 30)
        - St. John's Marsh (Box 30)
        - Strip Mining (Box 30)
      - Railroad Transportation (Box 30)
      - Revenue Sharing (Box 30)
      - Social Security (Box 30)
      - Taxation
        - General (Box 30)
        - Gasoline Tax (Box 30)
        - Marine Engine Tax (Box 30)
        - Tax Reform (Box 30)
  - Bills File
    The Bills File series includes the texts of bills sponsored or co-sponsored by O'Hara. There are also chronological and subject summaries of the bills introduced by O'Hara which indicate the action taken on the bills.
    - Summary of Legislation Introduced by O'Hara, 2 folders (Box 31)
    - 86th-92nd Congress 1959-1972 (Box 31)
    - 93rd-94th Congress 1973-1976 (Box 32)
  - Speeches
    The Speeches series contains texts and notes of speeches given by O'Hara. Included in the series are campaign speeches, commencement addresses, talks to professional groups and labor organizations, and occasional formal statements or testimony given before congressional or Democratic Party committees. "Speeches" given on the floor of the House, as recorded in the Congressional Record, are included in the Miscellaneous series. Several speeches on party reform have been filed in the Democratic Party series.
    - undated (Box 33)
    - 1959-1964 (Box 33)
    - 1965 (Box 33)
    - 1966 (Box 33)
    - undated, 1967-May 1967 (Box 33)
    - June-December 1967 (Box 33)
    - 1968 undated (Box 33)
    - undated 1968-February 1968 (Box 33)
    - March-December 1968 (Box 33)
    - undated 1969-May 1969 (Box 33)
    - June-October 1969 (Box 33)
    - November-December 1969 (Box 33)
    - undated January 1970 (Box 33)
    - February-September 1970 (Box 33)
    - October-December 1970 (Box 33)
    - 1971 (Box 33)
    - 1972 (Box 33)
    - January-July 1973 (Box 33)
    - August-October 1973 (Box 33)
    - November-December 1973 (Box 33)
    - 1974 undated (Box 34)
    - January-February 1974 (Box 34)
    - June-July 1974 (Box 34)
    - August-October 5, 1974 (Box 34)
    - October 6-December 1974 (Box 34)
    - January-March 1975 (Box 34)
    - April 1975 (Box 34)
    - May 1975 (Box 34)
    - June-July 1975 (Box 34)
    - August-October 15, 1975 (Box 34)
    - October 16-December 1975 (Box 34)
    - undated 1976-March 1976 (Box 34)
    - April-December 1976 (Box 34)
  - Public Relations
    The Public Relations series includes copies of O'Hara's congressional newsletter, 1960-1976, weekly newspaper column, 1960-1970, press releases, 1959-1976, transcripts of radio reports to the district, 1965-1967, and constituent questionnaires. Also included is an appearance file containing correspondence relating to O'Hara speaking engagements and material on Municipal Officials Conferences sponsored by O'Hara.
    - Newsletter 1960-1976 (Box 34)
    - Newspaper Column
      - 1960 (Box 34)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 34)
      - 1965 (Box 34)
      - 1966 (Box 34)
      - 1967 (Box 34)
      - 1968 (Box 34)
      - 1969 (Box 34)
      - 1970 (Box 34)
      - Articles for "Forest Teacher," 1967-1968 (Box 34)
    - Press Releases 1955-1976 (Box 35)
    - Radio Reports
      - 1965 (Box 36)
      - January-May 1966 (Box 36)
      - June-August 1966 (Box 36)
      - January-July 1967 (Box 36)
      - August-December 1967 (Box 36)
    - Constituent Questionnaire
      - 1962-1966 (Box 36)
      - 1967 (Box 36)
      - 1969 (Box 36)
      - 1970 (Box 36)
      - 1971 (Box 36)
      - 1972 (Box 36)
      - 1973 (Box 36)
      - 1974 (Box 36)
      - 1976 (Box 36)
    - Appearance File
      - 1963 (Box 36)
      - 1964 (Box 36)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 36)
      - 1969, 2 folders (Box 36)
      - 1970 (Box 36)
      - 1971, 2 folders (Box 36)
      - 1972 (Box 36)
    - Municipal Officials Conferences
      - August 16, 1965 (Box 36)
      - November 9-10, 1967 (Box 36)
      - March 6-7, 1969 (Box 36)
      - March 5-6, 1970 (Box 36)
      - April 25-26, 1974 (Box 36)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 37)
  - Political
    O'Hara's congressional campaigns, 1958-1974, and his 1976 senatorial campaign are documented in the Political series. The series is arranged chronologically and files for each campaign may include brochures and campaign literature, press releases, correspondence and memoranda, polling data, and position papers. There is usually a folder of material on O'Hara's opponent. Also filed in this series is one folder on the "Liberal Papers" incident which became an issue in the 1962 campaign, material from O'Hara's service as head of the Michigan Humphrey-Muskie campaign in 1968, and papers concerning O'Hara's campaign to succeed Carl Albert as House majority leader in 1971.
    - 1960 O'Hara Campaign (Box 38)
    - 1962 O'Hara Campaign, 3 folders (Box 38)
    - "The Liberal Papers" (Box 38)
    - George Romney (Box 38)
    - 1964 O'Hara Campaign, 3 folders (Box 38)
    - Right Wing Activity in Macomb County, 2 folders (Box 38)
    - 1966 O'Hara Campaign, 2 folders (Box 38)
    - 1968
      - O'Hara Campaign
        - Correspondence and Memoranda (Box 38)
        - District Opinion Survey (Box 38)
        - State Opinion Survey (Box 38)
      - Democratic National Convention, Credentials Committee (Box 38)
      - Humphrey Presidential Campaign, 3 folders (Box 38)
      - Michigan Conference of Concerned Democrats (Box 38)
    - 1970
      - O'Hara Campaign, 3 folders (Box 38)
    - House Majority Leader Contest, 5 folders (Box 39)
    - 1972
      - O'Hara Campaign
        - Brochures, etc. (Box 39)
        - Citizens for O'Hara Committee (Box 39)
        - Clippings (Box 39)
        - Correspondence and Memoranda (Box 39)
        - Fund Raising (Box 39)
        - Polls, 2 folders (Box 39)
        - Press Releases (Box 39)
        - Serotkin, Dave, 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Presidential Campaign, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - 1974 O'Hara Campaign
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 2 folders (Box 39)
      - District Polls, 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Tyza, Eugene (Box 39)
    - 1976 Senate Campaign
      - Announcement of Candidacy (Box 40)
      - Brochures, etc. (Box 40)
      - Candidates
        - Austin, Richard (Box 40)
        - Elsman, James (Box 40)
        - Riegle, Donald (Box 40)
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 5 folders (Box 40)
      - Educators for O'Hara (Box 40)
      - Endorsements (Box 40)
      - Issues Questionnaires (Box 40)
      - Labor for O'Hara Committee, 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Newsletter (Box 40)
      - Nominating Petitions (Box 40)
      - Organization and Strategy (Box 40)
      - Polls, 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Position Papers and Voting Records, 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Press Releases (Box 40)
      - Students for O'Hara Committee (Box 40)
      - Radio Transcripts (Box 40)
      - Voting Results (Box 40)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 41)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 42)
      (continued)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 43)
  - Democratic Party
    The Democratic Party series is comprised of material relating to O'Hara's chairmanship of the Commission on Rules of the Democratic National Committee and his service on other party committees and commissions in the period 1969-1975.
    - 1968 Convention Credentials Committee (Box 44)
    - O'Hara Rules Commission 1969-1972
      After the tumultuous events of 1968, the Democratic National Committee appointed two commissions to review the rules and procedures of the party and to recommend reforms to be implemented for the 1972 national convention. The Commission on Party Structure and Delegation Selection was first headed by George McGovern and then Donald Fraser.
      The Commission on Rules, which O'Hara chaired, was mandated to codify and study the rules of past Democratic conventions and to propose permanent rules for the committees of the convention and for the convention itself. O'Hara conducted a series of hearings and meetings across the country and his commission issued a final report entitled "Call to Order ..." The Commissions recommendations were presented to the Rules Committee of the 1972 Democratic Convention, of which O'Hara was also chairman.
      The O'Hara and McGovern-Fraser Commissions collaborated to prepare a draft charter for the party which was presented to the 1972 convention for consideration. The convention did not adopt the draft charter but did call for a Charter Commission to be established to prepare a party charter for consideration at a mid-term convention. O'Hara was appointed to the Charter Commission headed by Terry Sanford.